<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Simposio</title>
                <author xml:id="SF">Senofonte</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Codifica</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="DC">Diego Canali</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Supervisione</resp>
                    <persName xml:id="FT">Francesca Tomasi</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Portale Senofonte</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Università di Bologna</pubPlace>
                <date>2023</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Questa risorsa è liberamente accessibile per uso personale o scientifico.
                        Ogni uso commerciale è vietato.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Symposium By Xenophon of Athens. A new Critical Edition with a
                        Facing-Page English Translation</title>
                    <author ref="#SF">Senofonte</author>
                    <editor xml:id="DFJ">Donald F. Jackson</editor>
                    <publisher>The Edwin Mellen Press</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Lewinston, Queenston, Lampeter</pubPlace>
                    <date>2013</date>
                    <note> Nella presente edizione riporterò solamente il testo in lingua
                        greca</note>
                    <idno type="ISBN">ISBN 978-0-7734-4350-1</idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation marks="all"/>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>I trattini di sillabazione a fine riga sono stati eliminati e le parole
                        ricomposte</p>
                </hyphenation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>La codifica dei testi senofontei per la piattaforma Portale Senofonte sarà
                    descritta a tempo debito sul portale stesso</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person>
                        <persName ref="#SF" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/83270774"
                            >Senofonte</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="callia">Καλλίας</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="ipponico">Ἱππονίκος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="autolico">Αὐτολύκος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="nicerato">Νικήρατος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="socrate">Σωκράτης</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="critobulo">Κριτόβουλος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="ermogene">Ἑρμογένης</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="antistene">Ἀντισθένης</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="carmide">Χαρμίδης</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="protagora">Πρωταγόρα</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="gorgia">Γοργία</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="prodico">Προδίκος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="filippo">Φίλιππος</persName>
                        <persName xml:id="eros">Ἔρως</persName>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
            
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>The Symposium by Xenophon of Athens</head>
            <div xml:id="book_1_eng" n="1" xml:lang="english">
                <p n="1">1. To my mind it is worth while to relate not only the serious acts of
                    great and good men but also what they do in their lighter moods. I should like
                    to narrate an experience of mine that gives me this conviction.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It was on the occasion of the horse-races at the greater Panathenaic
                    games; <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName>, <persName ref="#ipponico"
                        >Hipponicus</persName>' son, was enamoured, as it happened, of the boy
                    <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName>, and in honour of his victory
                    in the pancratium1 had brought him to see the spectacle. When the racing was
                    over, <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName> proceeded on his way to his
                    house in the Peiraeus with <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName> and
                    the boy's father; <persName ref="#nicerato">Niceratus</persName> also was in his
                    company.</p>
                <p n="3">3. But on catching sight of a group comprising <persName ref="#socrate"
                    >Socrates</persName>, <persName ref="#critobulo">Critobulus</persName>,
                    <persName ref="#ermogene">Hermogenes</persName>, <persName ref="#antistene"
                        >Antisthenes</persName>, and <persName ref="#carmide">Charmides</persName>,
                    <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName> bade one of his servants escort
                    <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName> and the others, and himself
                    going over to <persName ref="#socrate">Socrates</persName> and his companions,
                    said,</p>
                <p n="4">4. “This is an opportune meeting, for I am about to give a dinner in honour
                    of <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName> and his father; and I think
                    that my entertainment would present a great deal more brilliance if my
                    dining-room were graced with the presence of men like you, whose hearts have
                    undergone philosophy's purification, than it would with generals and cavalry
                    commanders and office-seekers.”</p>
                <p n="5">5. “You are always quizzing us,” replied <persName ref="#socrate"
                    >Socrates</persName>; “for you have yourself paid a good deal of money for
                    wisdom to <persName ref="#protagora">Protagoras</persName>, <persName
                        ref="#gorgia">Gorgias</persName>, <persName ref="#prodico"
                            >Prodicus</persName>, and many others, while you see that we are what you
                    might call amateurs in philosophy; and so you feel supercilious toward us.”</p>
                <p n="6">6. “Yes,” said <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName>, “so far, I
                    admit, I have been keeping you ignorant of my ability at profound and lengthy
                    discourse; but now, if you will favour me with your company, I will prove to you
                    that I am a person of some consequence.”</p>
                <p n="7">7. Now at first <persName ref="#socrate">Socrates</persName> and his
                    companions thanked him for the invitation, as might be expected, but would not
                    promise to attend the banquet; when it became clear, however, that he was taking
                    their refusal very much to heart, they went with him. And so his guests arrived,
                    some having first taken their exercise and their rub-down, others with the
                    addition of a bath.</p>
                <p n="8">8. <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName> took a seat by his
                    father's side; the others, of course, reclined. A person who took note of the
                    course of events would have come at once to the conclusion that beauty is in its
                    essence something regal, especially when, as in the present case of <persName
                        ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName>, its possessor joins with it modesty
                    and sobriety.</p>
                <p n="9">9. For in the first place, just as the sudden glow of a light at night
                    draws all eyes to itself, so now the beauty of <persName ref="#autolico"
                        >Autolycus</persName> compelled every one to look at him. And again, there
                    was not one of the onlookers who did not feel his soul strangely stirred by the
                    boy; some of them grew quieter than before, others even assumed some kind of a
                    pose.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Now it is true that all who are under the influence of any of the gods
                    seem well worth gazing at; but whereas those who are possessed of the other gods
                    have a tendency to be sterner of countenance, more terrifying of voice, and more
                    vehement, those who are inspired by chaste <persName ref="#eros">Love</persName>
                    have a more tender look, subdue their voices to more gentle tones, and assume a
                    supremely noble bearing. Such was the demeanour of <persName ref="#callia"
                        >Callias</persName> at this time under the influence of <persName
                            ref="#eros">Love</persName>; and therefore he was an object well worth the
                    gaze of those initiated into the worship of this god.</p>
                <p n="11">11. The company, then, were feasting in silence, as though some one in
                    authority had commanded them to do so, when <persName ref="#filippo"
                        >Philip</persName> the buffoon knocked at the door and told the porter to
                    announce who he was and that he desired to be admitted; he added that with
                    regard to food he had come all prepared, in all varieties—to dine on some other
                    person's,—and that his servant was in great distress with the load he carried
                    of—nothing, and with having an empty stomach. Hearing this, <persName
                        ref="#callia">Callias</persName> said,</p>
                <p n="12">12. “Well, gentlemen, we cannot decently begrudge him at the least the
                    shelter of our roof; so let him come in.” With the words he cast a glance at
                    <persName ref="#autolico">Autolycus</persName>, obviously trying to make out
                    what he had thought of the pleasantry.</p>
                <p n="13">13. But <persName ref="#filippo">Philip</persName>, standing at the
                    threshold of the men's hall where the banquet was served, announced: “You all
                    know that I am a jester; and so I have come here with a will, thinking it more
                    of a joke to come to your dinner uninvited than to come by invitation.” “Well,
                    then,” said <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName>, “take a place; for the
                    guests, though well fed, as you observe, on seriousness, are perhaps rather ill
                    supplied with laughter.”</p>
                <p n="14">14. No sooner were they engaged in their dinner than <persName
                    ref="#filippo">Philip</persName> attempted a witticism, with a view to
                    rendering the service that secured him all his dinner engagements; but on
                    finding that he did not excite any laughter, he showed himself, for the time,
                    considerably vexed. A little later, however, he must try another jest; but when
                    they would not laugh at him this time either, he stopped while the dinner was in
                    full swing, covered his head with his cloak, and lay down on his couch.</p>
                <p n="15">15. “What does this mean, <persName ref="#filippo">Philip</persName>?”
                    <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName> inquired. “Are you seized with a
                    pain?” <persName ref="#filippo">Philip</persName> replied with a groan, “Yes,
                    <persName ref="#callia">Callias</persName>, by Heaven, with a severe one;
                    for since laughter has perished from the world, my business is ruined. For in
                    times past, the reason why I got invitations to dinner was that I might stir up
                    laughter among the guests and make them merry; but now, what will induce any one
                    to invite me? For I could no more turn serious than I could become immortal; and
                    certainly no one will invite me in the hope of a return invitation, as every one
                    knows that there is not a vestige of tradition of bringing dinner into my
                    house.” As he said this, he wiped his nose, and to judge by the sound, he was
                    evidently weeping. </p>
                <p n="16">16. All tried to comfort him with the promise that they would laugh next
                    time, and urged him to eat; and <persName ref="#critobulo">Critobulus</persName>
                    actually burst out into a guffaw at his lugubrious moaning. The moment <persName
                        ref="#filippo">Philip</persName> heard the laughter he uncovered his head,
                    and exhorting his spirit to be of good courage, in view of approaching
                    engagements,1 he fell to eating again.</p>
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
